<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://awxlong.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://awxlong.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-10-07T18:39:37+00:00</updated><id>https://awxlong.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Paradigms of AI modelling</title><link href="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/penta-paradigm-orig-bib-copy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paradigms of AI modelling"/><published>2023-07-12T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-12T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/penta-paradigm-orig-bib%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/penta-paradigm-orig-bib-copy/"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the 7 decades of the pursuit of artificial intelligence, this field has mainly dealt with the fundamental issue of knowledge representation and processing. Here are some modelling paradigms of AI:</p> <h1 id="symbolic-reasoning">Symbolic reasoning</h1> <ul> <li>Symbols can’t be differentiated</li> <li>What are symbols? Consider them logic predicates and ground atoms</li> <li>It takes a non-functional approach to modelling; a simple set of rules can lead to rich and diverse output (consider rules of grammar of certain language);</li> </ul> <h1 id="probabilistic-function-approximation">Probabilistic function approximation</h1> <ul> <li>Find a set of features that can map inputs to a set of outputs</li> <li>This mapping is always done from infinite domain to finite or infinite range, but never from finite domain to infinite range</li> </ul> <h1 id="reward-reinforcement">Reward reinforcement</h1> <ul> <li>Another non-functional approach aimed at designing an environment and an agent to maximize a reward signal within it.</li> </ul> <h1 id="causal-graphs">Causal graphs</h1> <ul> <li>Functional approach to modelling, but given the way in which information is stored, it allows causal interpretation of information beyond correlation.</li> </ul> <h1 id="meta">Meta</h1> <ul> <li>Modelling about modelling</li> <li>Meta learning, which involves automatically fine-tuning parameters</li> <li>meta-heuristics</li> </ul> <h1 id="mergers">Mergers</h1> <p>The above models can be assembled together to expand the capabilities of each, hopefully without compromising each other’s strenghts while mitigating their respective weaknesses:</p> <ul> <li>Knowledge graph embeddings</li> <li>Deep reinforcement learning</li> <li>Heuristic-driven machine learning methods</li> <li>Neuro-symbolic AI</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog-post"/><category term="food-for-though"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I share five different paradigms of modelling intelligence]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The dichotomy of Vision and Language</title><link href="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/dichotomy-orig-customblock/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The dichotomy of Vision and Language"/><published>2023-05-12T19:42:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-12T19:42:00+00:00</updated><id>https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/dichotomy-orig-customblock</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/dichotomy-orig-customblock/"><![CDATA[<p>Lex Fridman and Ilya Sutskever had an interesting AI Podcast at https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xoVibFYi1Gs</p> <p>An interesting question raised was where does vision starts and language ends, or viceversa. Here is a Venn Diagram which illustrates my opinion on this dichotomy:</p> <figure> <img src="/assets/img/vision-language.png" alt="Figure couldn't load due to an unknown error. Sorry."/> </figure> <p>I think our brain is not a monolith, in that there is a single algorithm underlying our perception, ability to speak a language, capacity for motor-control, memory, among others. Neuroscience divides and assigns different regions of the brains to different capacities. This is why patients, such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Molaison">patient H. M</a>, who have localized cerebral lesions may lose the capacity for memory, but not to speak.</p> <p>Given this premise, I think vision and language consitute such an example of capacities which are entangled in our mind (consider reading a book, where both faculties are active as you’re perceiving sentences from a page of it). However, despite entangled, I think we can try to unthread them, partly because there are also significant differences between them.</p> <p>I mainly associate our perceptual system with processing the external real world. I could also associate it with an internal imagery that reflects the real world, e.g., we can see memories of a trip somewhere in the past. I associate language, however, not with imagery but rather with the manipulation of symbols. Specifically, I think language is intricately tied to the manipulation of numbers, and being able to think of math. I think the linguistic capability to think of math can be distinguished from the perceptual system mainly because <em>math doesn’t exist in the real world, but rather in the abstract world</em>.</p> ]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog-post"/><category term="food-for-though"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[my comment on what is the relationship between the faculties of vision and language]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on Artificial General Intelligence</title><link href="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/agi-orig-audios/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on Artificial General Intelligence"/><published>2023-04-25T10:42:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-25T10:42:00+00:00</updated><id>https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/agi-orig-audios</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/agi-orig-audios/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="is-the-path-to-agi-clear">Is the path to AGI clear?</h1> <p><em>So, is the path to AGI clearly defined and is the quest of achieving AGI just a matter of time, computational resources and scalability?</em></p> <p>Because by following the current trajectory of making models larger and collecting larger datasets doesn’t address the issues of parsimony, explainability and subsequently trustworthiness, a simple answer to the rhetoric is “highly unlikely”.</p> <p>To elaborate on the answer, allow me to indulge on the basics of what AGI is, which would inevitably intermingled with the history of AI, the history of understanding Human Cognition. A pertinent starting point would be to reminisce on the millennia-old debate on nativism and empiricism. The former advocates that each Human Being is born with innate mental capacities or structures that are useful to make sense out of external sensory experience, while the latter says that a Human Being is born as “tabula rasa” (a white paper) who acquires knowledge from learning from environmental stimuli. As Human Knowledge grew over the years, and the debate permeated into several fields concerning the study of Humans, when faced with these dichotomies, a central theme of this book which is derived from the Yin-Yang is that the answer shouldn’t follow a zero-sum mentality, as in the correctness of one entails the incorrectness of the other. Rather, both hypotheses of human knowledge complement each other, and this is especially evident when we consider how these two schools of thoughts can address the limitations of each. Namely, the core issue of empiricism-based models of deep learning is its over-reliance of external data, to the point that the construction of these models have morphed from a scientific problem of understanding the mind to an engineering problem of how to extract the most knowledge from data, which fuels the pursuit of getting more data. Implications of this approach is that models which are proposed often fall into the issues of lack of parsimony, being black-boxes and hence aren’t trustworthy. A way to address them would arguably to develop the capability to reason about the environment, however, to give form to a structure for reasoning requires the machine to have its own language.</p> <h1 id="how-would-agi-look-like">How would AGI look like?</h1> <p>Hopefully, the preceding subsections have laid out concisely some of the current perspectives, challenges, and possible pathways the quest to first understanding what machine intelligence is, which would be a pre-requisite to achieving AGI. Despite being far from unravelling the mysteries of intelligence, we still have the freedom to indulge ourselves in imagining how would AGI look like, as in ponder what it is both conceptually and physically assuming we have already understood what algorithm breeds intelligence and managed to incorporate into a body which follows the biological principles of being alive. of One of the common misconceptions I’ll attempt in avoiding as best as a human as I can do is to prevent anthropomorphising the outlook of such AGI. Namely, an AGI doesn’t necessarily have to incorporate humanoid features. The argument for this is as follows: we human beings are by-product of evolution, which at its core dictates that the fundamental unit of life, the gene, should replicate. The engines of nature and probability shapes optimal templates for the fulfilment of such primaeval goals, however, these are not the best templates<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. In other words, the Human Being, our height, weight, facial features, method of replication, way of survival, way of organization, are but one template of the myriad of possibilities nature could have shaped a living being for the fulfilment of biological principles. As such, the design of AGI need not to replicate the successes of the Human Being, but rather enjoy the freedom of improving on it.</p> <p>Can the AI learn for itself? – there are several means to serve a biological principle, and random mutation is one of them. While our machines can undergo a controlled mutation as guided by the design of the environment, the cradle, from which it will nurture itself, we can make sure that its evolution doesn’t lead to precarious consequences for the good of humanity. This will not necessarily go against the biological principle of replication of components (organic or inorganic), because it can still be retained without random mutation.</p> <p>are not the purpose, but serve to a purpose. In other words, random mutations are not necessary, but rather useful mechanisms for adaptation. One can digitally bypass such mechanisms and still design an AI which follows the same principles of replication. Similarly, we acquiere energy from the sun from a lightly complex mechanism. This mechanism can be simplified by our engineered system to directly acquire energy. Is there anything lost? It’s an open question.</p> <h1 id="hardware-supplementing-what-biological-evolution-missed">Hardware: Supplementing what biological evolution missed</h1> <p>By abjuring from anthropomorphic biases, we can instrospect on ways to build a machine body that which is more optimal geared for survival. Consider, for instance, energy consumption. Our Human Bodies are a node of a complicated network of energy transfer, of which main (if not only) source of energy is the Sun. Plants convert solar energy to chemical energy through photosynthesis, which can be both transferred to humans directly or indirectly through non-human animals which consume them, as well as intermediate predators. Upon retrospect, however, such process can be artificially designed to be more straightforward and avoid “unnecessary detours”, so as to obtain energy directly for the sun in order to power the bodies of AGIs.</p> <p>Furthermore, our extremities are arguably optimal for survival thanks to our feet suitable for navigation, evolved to escape from predators, and hands to manipulate tools. The AGIs we design can inherit our adroitness in manipulating tools, but instead of getting feet we it’s arguably better to include wings or wheels which are better for optimal navigation and obstacle avoidance.</p> <h1 id="software-giving-form-to-the-black-box">Software: Giving form to the black box</h1> <p>An important step that is arguably important in the progress towards AGI is a focus on building an internal-state apparatus that would ascribe the properties of reasoning on machines, for it to develop a language from which we can give form to the black box. Because this language may follow mathematical principles, it has properties of self-reference which would allow for introspection, which is additional to the capabilities of current deep learning models which are mainly external and focus on extracting knowledge from environmental stimuli. The model, hence, should be able to:</p> <ul> <li>Prove Goldbach’s Conjecture and devise with new mathematical conjectures</li> <li>Be able to defeat humans in every benchmark possible that was designed on the basis of testing pattern extraction abilities and reasoning capabilities, including the Turing Test.</li> <li>Interact with the real world for both self-fulfilmment, and fulfilling its own purpose of understanding the world.</li> </ul> <h1 id="dangers-of-agi">Dangers of AGI</h1> <p>One of the most archaic moral principles an AGI can develop is that of reciprocity, that is, to react to mitigate damage inflicted upon It. If the source of damage is that of Human Activity or Collective Action, we can’t help but wonder whether It would react in a tit-for-tat fashion. Amidst this source of concern lurks, however, some relief given that this suggests that the AGI, through introspection of the Golden Rule, should be aware that mistreating us Humans would also be harmful for Itself given that we Humans can as much reciprocate damage inflicted upon us. Hence, it is an act of rationality not to take the first step towards cyclical doom. However, this relief is also interwoven with fear that certain Human, maybe out of curiosity or stupidity, decided through their irrational decision-making to harm the AGI, be harmed, and through the butterfly phenomenon open the Pandora Box.</p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>This is reminiscent of how in error minimization, we can hit local minima, rather than the global minimum. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog-post"/><category term="food-for-thought"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[is the quest of achieving AGI just a matter of time, computational resources and scalability?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on David Deutsch’s The Beginning of Infinity</title><link href="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/deutsch-orig-videos/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on David Deutsch’s The Beginning of Infinity"/><published>2023-01-20T21:42:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-20T21:42:00+00:00</updated><id>https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/deutsch-orig-videos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/deutsch-orig-videos/"><![CDATA[<figure> <img src="/assets/img/begin-infty.jpg" alt="Figure couldn't load due to an unknown error. Sorry."/> <figcaption id="chatgpt"> Cover of the book The Beginning of Infinity, extracted from https://www.amazon.co.uk/the-beginning-infinity-explanations-transform/dp/0140278168 </figcaption> </figure> <p><em>The Beginning of Infinity</em> is an enlightening book by David Deutsch. It sheds light into the nature of scientific progress, which consists not of extrapolating past successes, but rather exploring unanswered questions and propose a plethora of hypotheses in order to advance knowledge through trial and error.</p> <p>The Black Swann Philosophy<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> is perhaps a central tennet in Deutsch’s book. Namely, concerning the successful theories which try to explain certain phenomena in the real world, we should not ask why are they good, but rather how are they bad and how can they change to improve their causal, explanatory power.</p> <p>In order to make progress in any scientific field, we have to ask new and harder problems each time. Because any solution given to these problems is theory-laden<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, to improve on theories we need new problems which guide new theories. The path to a good answer or theory is not straight, but rather bent. In searching for a good theory/explanation/answer to a problem, we may have to take a detour in identifying tangential problems that could, maybe luckily, help us answer an original question.</p> <p>This has made me reflect on how we should make progress in artificial intelligence. On one hand, we can gaze at the current successes in the history of AI and expand on deep learning.</p> <p>Well, ever since the start of the 21st century, thanks to the increase of computational power and omni-presence of data, what used to be small neural networks that could only approximate Boolean logic or very small-scale digit recognition have scaled up to large deep learning models which are achieving state-of-the art performance on several benchmarks meant to measure a certain faculty of human intelligence: human vision or NLP through QA. What empowers these results are the well-deserved research poured into deep learning which explore novel architectures, and optimization techniques, thus redefining the new state-of-the-art performance on several canonical benchmarks. See for instance how interest on deep learning have increased six-fold over the past decade according to <d-cite key="zhang_2021_chapter"></d-cite>.</p> <p>From this trend of successes, one can ask: how can we go beyond current state-of-the-art performance? Successes in deep learning suggest that we can further extrapolate deep learning’s infrastructure, which should map to increases in functional performance. See an analysis done <d-cite key="kaplan_2020_scaling"></d-cite> on neural language models, which showed that language modeling performance improved smoothly as the neural model’s size, dataset size, and amount of compute used for training increased. We can refer to this idea of scaling deep neural networks as the scaling hypothesis:</p> <p>However, careful observers have noted that there are some very problematic caveats to the scaling hypothesis. It’s the (ignored) elephant of in the room. Namely:</p> <ol> <li>brittleness due to inability for robust generalization beyond the training set distribution,</li> <li>lack of explainability tied to the lack of computational semantics,</li> <li>and lack of parsimony due to this evident over-reliance to big data, and unacceptable levels of computational power consumption as argued by Garcez &amp; Lamb, (2020)</li> <li>benchmarks with misleading metrics of success and design. For example, ImageNet contain biases such as object-centric bias, i.e. images tend to show the object to be classified centred, without being rotated, well-illuminated, and without confounding objects <d-cite key="barbu_2019_objectnet"></d-cite></li> </ol> <p>Given the current issues, we can return to the original question of can we make further progress in AI. Thanks to David Deutsch’s book, I feel like we shouldn’t rely only on extrapolating current successes, i.e., scaling current transformer-based models and hope for the emergence of intelligence.</p> <p>We may have to revisit the original questions that kickstarted the field AI, revise our underlying assumptions, and propose novel hypotheses:</p> <ul> <li>what can we do beyond prediction error minimization with neural networks? Or what is something novel we can do in addition to learning how to regenerate a given dataset?</li> <li>what can we do to optimize search during logical deduction over a combinatorial growing space of pieces of knoweldge?</li> <li>what consitutes a good representation of data? Do we even <em>need</em> a representation of the data?</li> </ul> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote"> <p>the Black Swann Philosophy gears us to think that a good theory not only explain why a natural phenomena happens this way, but also why it doesn’t happen in another way. The story behind it is that if you want to prove that all swans in the park are white, you shouldn’t think about searching only for white swans, but also actively look for black ones. If actively trying to disprove your hypothesis fails, then your hypothesis is robust to counter-arguments. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>My interpretation of “theory-laden” is that we can only formulate hypotheses based on the conclusion we want to reach. Thus, in order to reach novel conclusions, we have to endlessly hypothesize. Hence the book’s title is The Beginning of Infinity. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog-post"/><category term="books-review"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[my review of the book The Beginning of Infinity by David Deutsch grounded on the topic of artificial intelligence.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are you Clever Hans or are you actually clever, Hans?</title><link href="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/clevr-hans-orig-videos/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are you Clever Hans or are you actually clever, Hans?"/><published>2023-01-12T21:42:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-12T21:42:00+00:00</updated><id>https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/clevr-hans-orig-videos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2023/clevr-hans-orig-videos/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Author’s update on October, 2023</strong>: I wrote this satirical article a few months after Gato and ChatGPT’s release, particularly after having some conversation with ChatGPT. Nowadays, a few of the claims, such as in <a href="#chatgpt">Figure 1</a>, I made back then are less valid. GPT-4 (although it is paid) can now retrieve information online, meaning it <em>can</em> synthesize valid links. It can also solve math problems more accurately. This is partly because for prompts about calculations or theorem proofs it can retrieve an answer from online calculators or provers like WolframAlpha, in addition to its own improvement due to scaling. I’m still skeptical scaling this architecture is the right way forward, but maybe I’m delusional and LLMs are the next step forward for AI…</p> <p>Somewhere, an influential research group from a highly respected academic sphere published a report that the model they have designed has gotten us humans closer to AGI. They named it HANS, short for Human ANd Smart, and documented that the model consists of a generalist agent who can multi-task: it can play a series of Atari games which denote its ability to interact with a digital environment, hold a quotidian conversation which reflects its dominion of Human English Language, and caption images to show its prowess in image recognition. Because the model was built using a single transformer neural network trained on diverse data, it was originally advertised as evidence that the path to AGI is clear: create a bigger model trained on a larger dataset. Media communicators, however, may have “misunderstood” the message (either intentionally or not), and instead transmitted the overhyped sentiment that this model was a precursor to AGI and suggested it would bring with itself a lot of existential crisis to the unprepared Human society. In the end, what better way to endanger humanity than predicting the next output given some input.</p> <p>Furthermore, they claimed that there were primitive signs of sentiency in the model after one of the research engineer held and released a private conversation transcript with him/her on topics about physics and emerged from it convinced that he was talking to a 7-8 years old child.</p> <p>The above hypothetical scenario is an amalgamation on real-life cases of research groups from Google who have designed models resembling some degree of Human Intelligence on very constrained areas such as multitasking or domain-specific conversation. Please see Gato, a multitasking agent designed by <d-cite key="reed_2022_a"></d-cite> and a subsequent report documenting what it is and what effect it instigated in the public <d-cite key="heikkil_2022_the"></d-cite>. I’ve also included the articles by <d-cite key="sparkes_2022_has, tiku_2022_the"></d-cite> where they have reported on how Google left one of its engineer on paid administrative leave for making claims that one of its language models, called LaMDa, was sentient as a 7-8 years old child after holding a conversation with it on <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2021/05/20/1025135/ai-large-language-models-bigscience-project/">physics</a>. I’ve modified some names, such as changing Gato’s name to HANS to fulfil the (very) important goal of making a pun in the subtitle.</p> <p>Gato, ChatGPT and other enormous, pretrained transformer-based neural networks are mostly arcane models which are inoperable to the common citizen not endowed with high-end computing hardware and software. Their release ignited a catharsis of emotions amongst the public. From opposite sides of the spectrum, there were those who aggrandized their anxiety over existential threats, and there were those sceptics who pointed out that such claims were, essentially, non-sensical. A model that is trained on conveniently, readily available, vast-amount of high-quality compiled dataset reflect not its generalizing capability but rather its overreliance on data, lack of parsimony and the ever-present issue of explainability with these black-box models. Another interesting set of issues is the inconsistent inability to do math, as displayed by ChatGPT:</p> <figure> <img src="/assets/img/chatGPT-math.png" alt="Figure couldn't load due to an unknown error. Sorry."/> <figcaption id="chatgpt"> Figure 1: GPT-3-powered model like ChatGPT can't do math properly, probably because it doesn't understand the notion of algebra, geometry, calculus, among other branches. ChatGPT also fail to provide correct or real links to websites, as well as can't carry out instructions like "don't say anything". </figcaption> </figure> <p>In general, GPT-3 powered large language models may struggle to synthesize deterministic output: those of universal nature, i.e., doesn’t change regardless of context. Examples include math equations (as shown above), or links to websites.</p> <p>Hence, there exist at least some scepticism who wonder whether the model HANS is actually clever, or whether it’s simply reminiscent of clever Hans.</p> ]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog-post"/><category term="food-for-thought"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[my (mostly satirical) comments on ChatGPT and Gato, large, transformer-based models that shook the AI community on 2022]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The intuition behind Frequentist linear regression, Bayesian linear regression and Gaussian Processes</title><link href="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2022/analogy-freq-bay-gp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The intuition behind Frequentist linear regression, Bayesian linear regression and Gaussian Processes"/><published>2022-12-15T13:42:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-15T13:42:00+00:00</updated><id>https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2022/analogy-freq-bay-gp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2022/analogy-freq-bay-gp/"><![CDATA[<p>A consequence of believing in the consilience of knowledge is that we believe all knowledge is connected. We can make analogies amongst pieces of knowledge that can help us understand them.</p> <p>One thing I like to do with analogies is to grasp some intuition behind probabilistic models, which I hope is useful for concepts which are inherently hard to undersatnd such as Bayesianism, especially if you are accustomed to frequentist statistical modelling.</p> <p>The following hopefully helps you distinguish frequentist linear regression, from Bayesian linear regression, and Gaussian processes. It is worth noting that this article is NOT technical in terms of probability theory, and I recommend going through the Recommended Reading before continuing.</p> <h1 id="frequentist-linear-regression">Frequentist linear regression:</h1> <p>Imagine that on a sheet of paper with some dots drawn on them, you ask yourself how can you place a ruler to fit those dots. You only place a unique ruler. This ruler can be of any shape, whether it’s a grader, straight or triangular ruler.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/freq.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Image extracted from http://kkjkok.blogspot.com/2013/03/introduction-to-machine-learning-part-2.html </div> <h1 id="bayesian-linear-regression">Bayesian linear regression:</h1> <p>On the same sheet of paper, I just have a belief of all possible rulers that can fit those dots. No single ruler is actually placed. Rulers here can have a variety of shapes, and can be assembled together (analogous to basis functions applied to input features). The rulers may be rugged, so whenever you draw some lines with the rulers (analogous to evaluating the model), you get slightly different lines each time (to denote uncertainty or noise inherent to the parameters of the model)</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/bayes.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Image extracted from https://towardsdatascience.com/bayesian-regression-with-implementation-in-r-fa71396dd59e </div> <h1 id="gaussian-process">Gaussian process:</h1> <p>On the same sheet of paper with dots, I only hold the belief of what are all the plausible lines that can go through the dots. The absence of a ruler is to denote that a GP is typically non-parametric and models the function space directly. The analogy to the prior belief here is that before even given the paper, I have some sort of intuition as to what lines are plausible, with the constraint that I have to believe in lines (this is mathematically expressed by the Kernel which isn’t a diagonal matrix, therefore points of the lines are not independent to one another). As I observe datapoints during training, I can both guide the trajectory of the lines, and ignore prior lines which clearly don’t fit the dots.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/gp.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Image extracted from https://thegradient.pub/gaussian-process-not-quite-for-dummies/ </div> <h1 id="recommended-reading">Recommended Reading</h1> <p>For the technical details behind linear regression, with and without the Bayesian treatment, along with Gaussian Processes, I recommend reading either of these freely available textbooks:</p> <ul> <li>Murphy, Kevin P. (2022) Probabilistic Machine Learning: An Introduction. https://probml.github.io/pml-book/book1.html</li> <li>Bishop, Christopher (2006) Pattern Recognition and Machine Learning. https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/publication/pattern-recognition-machine-learning/</li> </ul> <p>P.S.: To me, Murphy’s book is more recent, but discusses topics in a more straightforward manner. Murphy also has available code to run. <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/publication/pattern-recognition-machine-learning/">Bishop</a> goes into a bit more detail, but his notation is a bit outdated.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog-post"/><category term="class-notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I use analogies to grasp the intuition of the differences behind frequentism, bayesianism and Gaussian processes]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deciding when to use narrow AI-based or heuristic-driven solutions for a problem</title><link href="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2022/narrow-ai-orig-jupyter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deciding when to use narrow AI-based or heuristic-driven solutions for a problem"/><published>2022-02-06T12:42:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-06T12:42:00+00:00</updated><id>https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2022/narrow-ai-orig-jupyter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2022/narrow-ai-orig-jupyter/"><![CDATA[<p>For the original notebook, please go to my respective <a href="https://github.com/awxlong/notes-re/blob/main/narrow-ai-vs-heuristic/On%20the%20decision%20of%20using%20narrow%20AI-based%20or%20heuristic-driven%20solutions.ipynb">repository</a></p> <p>What follows is an embedded notebook:</p> <div class="jupyter-notebook" style="position: relative; width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;"> <div class="jupyter-notebook-iframe-container"> <iframe src="/assets/jupyter/narrow_heuristic.ipynb.html" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; border-style: none;" width="100%" height="100%" onload="this.parentElement.style.paddingBottom = (this.contentWindow.document.documentElement.scrollHeight + 10) + 'px'"></iframe> </div> </div> ]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog-post"/><category term="class-notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[some thoughts concerning the decision to leverage or not artificial intelligence to tackle a problem]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The (Small) Extended Handbook for Undergraduate Math</title><link href="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2022/meaning-math-orig-redirect/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The (Small) Extended Handbook for Undergraduate Math"/><published>2022-02-01T17:42:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-01T17:42:00+00:00</updated><id>https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2022/meaning-math-orig-redirect</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2022/meaning-math-orig-redirect/"><![CDATA[<p>Redirecting to another page.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[you can also redirect to assets like pdf]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Three tips to consider when revising for a challenging test</title><link href="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2021/revision-orig-sidetoc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three tips to consider when revising for a challenging test"/><published>2021-11-25T14:42:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-25T14:42:00+00:00</updated><id>https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2021/revision-orig-sidetoc</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2021/revision-orig-sidetoc/"><![CDATA[<p>Pupils may often struggle to find a learning strategy to increase their score for a test. The following is a list of 3 tips that can be considered when revising for an exam:</p> <h1 id="1-the-myth-of-learning-modality">1. The myth of learning modality</h1> <p>There is no need to spend time searching for a learning modality that matches your revision style. If you’re someone who enjoys reading, that doesn’t necessarily mean that you can’t try studying through visual aids like diagrams that help you simplify the content from certain topic. Nor does it mean that you can’t listen to lectures while doing your daily chores. Recent evidence, such as that from <d-cite key="aslaksen_2018_the"></d-cite> where they did a small meta-analysis of 10 papers on learning modalities, suggests that there is no enhanced learning outcome when aligning preference to modality-specific learning styles.</p> <figure> <img src="/assets/img/learning-modality.png" alt="Figure couldn't load due to an unknown error. Sorry."/> <figcaption> Try either learning style. Source: https://www.businessedge.org.nz/jeanette-bremner-visual-thinking-strategies/ </figcaption> </figure> <h1 id="2-distributed-consistent-learning">2. Distributed, consistent learning</h1> <p>Well, what works then? A common idea echoed by educational psychologists is that spaced learning, also known as distributed practice, has a significant positive effect on learning outcome as measured by retention interval. As shown by <d-cite key="cepeda_2006_distributed, janiszewski_2003_a"></d-cite>, students tend to have a higher recall of verbal stimuli when it’s presented over spaced episodes compared to when presented over a massed session. What we can extrapolate is that we shouldn’t learn a lot during a single session, but rather distribute learning across different smaller, but more frequent ones. Even more, <d-cite key="carvalho_2020_selfregulated"></d-cite> has shown that spaced learning also works when students properly self-regulate their study during a massive open online course and correlated positively with quiz performance. These results are indeed relevant for the situation a lot of us pupils are subject to due to the pandemic.</p> <figure> <img src="/assets/img/dist-learning.jpg" alt="Figure couldn't load due to an unknown error. Sorry."/> <figcaption> Distribute it, instead of cramming it. Source: https://www.jcrsmed.org/articles/2018/4/1/images/JCurrResSciMed_2018_4_1_37_233198_f1.jpg </figcaption> </figure> <h1 id="3-self-test">3. Self-test</h1> <p>Another tip worth considering is to constantly self-test yourself on what you learnt, instead of only restudying the same information. Reviews like that from <d-cite key="roediger_2011_the"></d-cite> has identified that the active, repeated retrieval of information from memory produces better retention of such compared to conventional ways of passive learning such as watching lectures, having study groups, or reading. For example, search in the internet for quizzes made by fellow peers or past papers that get released after a period of examination is over, and enjoy doing them. If there is feedback readily available, it’s recommended for you to delay the feedback as it has been shown by the same author <d-cite key="roediger_2011_the"></d-cite> that it may prove to yield better learning outcome than immediate feedback.</p> <p>So, this may sound cliché, but… what were the three tips I just shared? Self-test yourself.</p> <figure> <img src="/assets/img/joke-self-test.jpg" alt="Figure couldn't load due to an unknown error. Sorry."/> <figcaption> Also, this illustration is perhaps not “exactly” the self-testing you just had in mind, but it’s more or less the same principle of actively participating in a task[^1]. Source: https://lumiradxcaresolutions.com/2016/11/08/what-is-patient-self-care-dr-mark-sullivan/ </figcaption> </figure> <p>Of course, fine-grain details such as how much time do you dedicate to self-testing, or duration in between your spaced sessions as well as which modalities to try may ultimately be up to you to decide. In the end, this depends on your individual context and available resources.</p> <p>Finally, the three tips are complementary to one another. As such, when spacing your study, find some time you can dedicate to self-test. Or otherwise experiment with different learning modalities and test yourself in each of them.</p> <p>All in all, I hope these tips come in handy when revising for any challenging test!</p> ]]></content><author><name>An Xuelong</name></author><category term="blog-post"/><category term="class-notes"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[three tips I share to revise for a (challenging) exam]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review on Sapiens and Homo deus by Yuval Harari</title><link href="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2021/yuval-orig-math/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review on Sapiens and Homo deus by Yuval Harari"/><published>2021-10-08T15:42:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-08T15:42:00+00:00</updated><id>https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2021/yuval-orig-math</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://awxlong.github.io/blog/2021/yuval-orig-math/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="overview">Overview</h1> <p><strong>What does it mean to be human? What does it mean to exist? What is being <em>Homo sapiens</em>?</strong></p> <figure> <img src="/assets/img/deus.jpg" alt="Figure couldn't load due to an unknown error. Sorry."/> <figcaption id="homo-deus"> Illustration 1: digital book cover of Homo Deus authored by Yuval Harari </figcaption> </figure> <p>Sapiens<d-cite key="harari_2019_sapiens"></d-cite> and Homo Deus<d-cite key="harari_2015_homo"></d-cite> are books authored by Yuval Harari. Both of them are thought provocative and discusses how we, the species known as <em>Homo sapiens</em>, came to be as we now are, and discusses some of the paths in which we may embark ourselves. I don’t seek to provide a summary of the books per se, but rather discuss some of the after thoughts from reading them. For instance, I’d mention some of the fundamental principles of human behavior I’ve identified in the book. I believe that a mention and discussion of these fundamental traits of human beings would assist us in enlightening possible future steps to achieve the next level of artificial intelligence, a field I’m interested on. Finally, I hope this also ignite some curiosity towards the mysteries lingering behind the mask we call “humanity”, and from this curiosity we can unveil the answers to questions like “who we are?”, “how did we become like this?”, “what will come next for us?”, among others.</p> <h1 id="1-intolerance-and-our-drive-to-change-ourselves">1. Intolerance and our drive to change ourselves</h1> <h2 id="how-did-we-arrive-to-the-present">How did we arrive to the present?</h2> <p>Some of the intriguing questions that were discussed in Sapiens is why <em>Homo sapiens</em> is the sole species that stood until the present day to become the most powerful organism governing every other remaining species. Indeed, it was strange to me that given the existence of Homo erectus or Neanderthal, why is it that <em>Homo sapiens</em> is the only one that remained.</p> <p>A viable hypothesis is that a fundamental trait, albeit not unique, of <em>Homo sapiens</em> is that we are intolerant. Our intolerance to different species is what perhaps drove our competitive and lethal behavior that may have extinguished these species. The remnants of such intolerance that we inherited from our ancestors can be perhaps witnessed in how today’s humans can still get at each other’s throats for trivial issues such as different ideologies or ethnicity. Not even a century has passed since World War II has ended.</p> <p>Of course, intolerance is not necessarily something to be viewed as exclusively negative and something that ends up guiding <em>Homo sapiens</em> to engage in brutal competition or deadly fights to emerge victorious until the present. Intolerance is also what perhaps drove us to achieve our current advances in technology, and build highly efficient civilizations that permit the exploration of outer space and soon the colonization of other planets. Here, I’ll use a very intuitive definition for intolerance, which is to not conform with a present situation. In Sapiens, a recurrent theme throughout the book is that a lot of the commodities we have nowadays, such as a personal computer, smart phone, public transportation, hygiene, a society with all of its institutions such as schools, business corporations, among other things, aren’t actually necessary, at least in terms of biology. Our basic biology can be simply satisfied by an adequate supply of food and reproduction through finding a partner. In short, survival and reproduction were perhaps the fundamental reason to exist since <em>Homo sapiens</em>, and by that regard any other species, appeared on Planet Earth. What makes <em>Homo sapiens</em> distinct from other species is that we don’t only behave within the boundaries set by our natural, objective needs of survival. We can step beyond our biology and interact with the environment and with each other to manufacture new purposes of life, new subjective needs (in the book this process was known as revolutionizing our cognition). Art, religion, science, economy and politics, and along with it war and poverty all emerged partly due to our intolerance towards the boundaries of the survival instincts that we’re born with. Conversely, we can imagine how simple today’s society would be if we only sticked to our basic, natural instincts of survival: there won’t be private and public institutions promulgating the rule of law, nor promoting scientific research and development to enhance our livelihoods. We might be simply roaming around the vast fields on Earth and preying on whatever sustain our being.</p> <h1 id="2-mass-coordination-and-our-drive-to-become-more-powerful">2. Mass coordination and our drive to become more powerful</h1> <p>The irony of human life is that although we’re intolerant to each other’s differences, we can nonetheless set aside such intolerance and achieve a very flexible, highly-efficient cooperation between one another to achieve great deeds that ultimately positioned ourselves not only on top of the food chain, but also placed us closer to space, the moon and other celestial bodies. In Homo Deus, another set of intriguing question involved asking why haven’t bees, insects that can organize so efficiently between themselves, built nuclear weapons like us humans did. Why haven’t elephants, or other species that have displayed some level of capacity to band themselves to fend off predators or cooperate between themselves, conquered humans like we conquer them. A viable answer to that is that <em>Homo sapiens</em> is perhaps the sole species in the entire planet (and maybe Universe), to efficiently make use of language to communicate with one another and coordinate ourselves into groups to deal with the dangers that other species and the environment posed to us. Here, the fabric that holds together this assembly of humans is something called intersubjectivity, as mentioned in both books (<a href="#deus1">Figure 1</a>).</p> <figure> <img src="/assets/img/homo-deus1.png" alt="Figure couldn't load due to an unknown error. Sorry."/> <figcaption id="deus1">Figure 1: From both Sapiens and Homo Deus, it could be extrapolated that the foundation for mass cooperation between _Homo sapiens_ is the intersubjective belief that this mass cooperation is beneficial and therefore it’s desirable to go along with it. The reason why this massive assemblies of humans don’t settle in for a sedentary, unchanging life in hiatus may be explained by the intolerant nature of _Homo sapiens_ that drove this species to explore the unknown (science and technology), improve its own livelihood through better private and political institutions, and along with it wage endless wars. </figcaption> </figure> <p>Of course, one could be curious as to why the formation of this intersubjective, collective thought that mass cooperation is good didn’t lead <em>Homo sapiens</em> into living stagnant lives, without much change in their lifestyles as if it was in hiatus, but has rather guided this species into changing so much as to become the unabated top predator of the food chain, the undefeated organism that can conquer illnesses, explore space and is currently finding paths to immortality and create artificially intelligent entities. This is in sharp contrast with how <em>Homo sapiens</em> looked like ages ago. The fuel behind is perhaps what was discussed above: the intolerant nature that <em>Homo sapiens</em> was born with, and that is passed down through generations.</p> <p>To understand the above, we can look at this from another perspective. We can imagine what would have happened if our ancestors didn’t have the capability nor desire to group themselves into large civilizations, but rather settle themselves into small groups of hunter-gatherers or small villages of farmers. In other words, they may have formed systems of believes that justified and encouraged some actions such as hunting and agriculture but didn’t really seek cooperation nor sharing these beliefs between themselves. If that’s the case there wouldn’t exist complex entities such as villages, nor empires, nor nations. We could also ask what if our ancestors did assemble at a massive scale by reinforcing this set of inter-subjective believes to form communities, villages, empires or nations. Nonetheless, this massively organized assembly wasn’t built with the purpose of changing its own status (for better or for worse), but rather to just maintain it. In other words, they banded into large-scale groups just to “watch the days pass together”, “contemplate the cycles of the sun and moon”, “hunt to survive, but don’t do anything else to disturb nature”, without ever asking whether one day a collective effort could revolutionize lifestyles, that collective effort could send humans to the moon, that collective effort could dominate any other ferocious species that may have once scared them or that collective effort could lead them to a different, better future.</p> <p>Regardless of which scenario above is examined, it’s very likely that in each, we, <em>Homo sapiens</em>, may have been extinguished or conquered by a species that was capable of achieving that highly proficient level of mass coordination fueled by greedy-intolerant ambitions, similar to how we’ve sent countless other species to extinction by feeding on them or subverted other species like chimpanzees to zoos for entertainment and rats to laboratories for science. None other species, not elephants, nor bees, not chimps nor rats, who have indeed shown some level of mass cooperation, can organize themselves into such a succinctly designed assembly and be so well coordinated no matter how different they are like <em>Homo sapiens</em>. Let alone mention how other species other than <em>Homo sapiens</em> could have ambitions to improve their own situation, build intelligent machines, or explore outer space.</p> <p>All in all, the synchrony between intolerance and mass coordination sustained by a collective, intersubjective belief may sound unstable, but it’s this beautiful myth that constitutes part of the reason of why us humans, <em>Homo sapiens</em>, achieved our current status in history, which is in sharp contrast with other species such as Homo erectus or Neanderthals that have gone unreasonably extinct, or chimps and fish, that have become subverted by us without obvious reasons.</p> <h1 id="intolerance-and-mass-coordination-for-artificial-intelligence">Intolerance and mass coordination for artificial intelligence</h1> <p>On a completely different note, owed to my interest in AI, when reading about these fundamental aspects of humanity, it sparked in me an interest in how these aspects (mass cooperation, intersubjectivity, intolerance). Given the current progress in AI, we could ask intriguing questions as follows.</p> <blockquote> <p>How would AI look like if the different models that have achieved landmark achievements such as GPT-3 or AlphaFold were to merge or cooperate between one another, just like how humans from completely different civilizations worked together in human history? This chimeric model (<a href="#deus2">Figure 2</a>) would be capable of performing diverse tasks depending on the input that it perceives. These tasks may range from reading comprehension to protein structure prediction, to disease prognosis and autonomous driving.</p> </blockquote> <figure> <img src="/assets/img/homo-deus2.png" alt="Figure couldn't load due to an unknown error. Sorry."/> <figcaption id="deus2">Figure 2: schematization of the chimeric model meant to expand the current capacities of AI. This is done by, simply, merging the models that have achieved landmark results in the different competitions in a subfield of intelligence. </figcaption> </figure> <p>Of course, <a href="#deus2">Figure 2</a> is just a rough draft from which a plethora of practical concerns arise: how many models will it have to merge? What are the boundaries of each model added? Is this architecture scalable? Among others. Nonetheless, the underlying analogy to draw here is that just as how different humans can cooperate at a massive scale, I envision that the next step to get closer to general intelligence is to somehow be able to merge all these different models or to form certain connection among them.</p> <p>Harari has summarized quiet precisely that in biological terms, organisms’ sole purpose of existence is to survive and reproduce. Through natural selection, one species, like <em>Homo sapiens</em>, which is by nature intolerant and capable of achieving mass coordination through developing intersubjective believes, became the most powerful entity on Earth. Nonetheless, AI is not only not a biological entity, but also devoid of a purpose of existence. What are the “survive and reproduce”[^1] equivalents for AI, and how will AI evolve from those basic needs into also becoming “intolerant”, developing “intersubjective beliefs to massively coordinate” other AI models like the chimeric model in <a href="#deus2">Figure 2</a>, and subsequently displace <em>Homo sapiens</em> as the most powerful entity on Earth, or even larger, in the Milky Way or Universe. Therefore,</p> <blockquote> <p>… from another perspective, will we be able to embed in a machine a value function resembling the survival instincts of human beings, such that this value function can somehow guide the machine into evolving and developing complicated, yet intricate networks of machines to cooperate with one another into further enhancing this value function?</p> </blockquote> <p>With all the talk about AI above, it seems as if only we, <em>Homo sapiens</em>, shaped AI. Nonetheless, I believe we should be open to the idea that AI can also change us. For example, the pursuit of artificial intelligence has changed how we view intelligence, cognition, perception, among other mysterious human faculties that we don’t understand thoroughly, yet. AI, and its symbiosis with other sectors of society such as healthcare, education or economy will also have a deep impact in our lifestyles. Given this premise, we <em>Homo sapiens</em> can reflect on how our intersubjective realm is going to morph in response to how AI advances. Although Harari wasn’t specifically referring to AI, the following are quiet interesting ways to redefine some of the mysterious faculties we humans have:</p> <ul> <li>“feelings”: inaccurate term used to describe a collection of neuronal signaling. But then, I believe a natural question that follows then is what initiates this cascade of neuronal firing: external input, internal structure, or both?</li> <li>“Emotion”: a biochemical algorithm of neuronal signaling.</li> <li>“consciousness”: term to describe feelings and mental imagery (representation of our perception).</li> </ul> <p>Theoretically, this suggests that with a digital neural network, e.g. a deep neural network, that’s meant to simulate neural signaling would be able to model these human traits, even if the end result is not necessarily “within our expectations of what feelings, emotion and consciousness are”. For example, to me, the advances of image recognition have provided me with the following definition to “understanding”, which is to be able to have some higher level neurons fire probabilistically in response to the low level firing of neurons given an determined input stream. This is in sharp contrast with common definitions that advocates “understanding” assimilated a “meaning” that’s associated to an entity of the world, or somewhere along the lines. Of course, although there seems to be a more down-to-earth, precise, biological and mathematical definition to “understanding” that may be in contrast to a lot of our expectations (including me), it seems as though this is where we might be induced to think due to the rapid development of AI that’s going against much of the paradigms we believed in the past and present. As a side node, I’ll fervently encourage all of us to think not in tune with the current norms, since in this way we tend to reinforce our current paradigms, but rather to focus our studies and reflections on what’s different to the norm, since in this way we can explore and inquire into the unknown.</p> <p>It’s worth noting though that the above inquiries concerning the future development of AI revolves around our understanding of human beings, particularly <em>Homo sapiens</em>. Nonetheless, though <em>Homo sapiens</em> is very likely to be the dominant species in the world, it’s not the only one. The future steps could also draw some inspirations from other species as well. For instance, bats perceive the world through echolocation, so would this trait enhance AI?</p> <h1 id="but-in-the-end-are-we-happy">But in the end… are we happy?</h1> <p>I have attempted to share my thoughts on Yuval Harari’s two books on how we came to be as we are today (due to our intolerance to how we’re born and to those around us), as well as discussed where we might be heading, mainly by drawing parallels with the development of AI. However, just like author Harari, I wanted to ask, are we happy? As in, are we happy about with our current understanding of human nature? Are we happy about how we envision where we might be heading? These are some questions that dissolves itself into the abyss of neglect during our pursuit of understanding ourselves and of higher grounds of humanity.</p> <p>Of course, how do we define happiness to begin with anyway. Harari shared a simple definition, which is that happiness is a byproduct when our expectations meet reality, or vice-versa. We, <em>Homo sapiens</em>, have efficiently managed to survive until the present day, and through our intolerance to our previous selves, previous ways of living, we managed to climb to the top of the food chain and govern planet Earth. Nowadays, we’re in a crossroad where we get to decide to where we’re heading to, and whether the path chosen makes us happier, as in having our expectations driven by intolerance met, or make us more intolerant, as in having wilder, more ambitious expectations.</p> <p>The questions I’ll want to ask of course in this final section, given the plethora of possibilities that the understanding of human nature and progress in AI bring, are:</p> <blockquote> <p>Will our understanding of emotions and feelings help us become happier, or will it lead us to live in a society saturated by experiences such that there would be nothing else to make us happier?</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>Will the symbiosis of AI with the different sectors of society (Healthcare, Economy, Education, among others) satisfy our needs or just produce even more needs?</p> </blockquote> <p>All in all, Sapiens and Homo Deus are two books authored by Yuval Harari that I highly recommend reading. Although both their themes don’t specifically revolve around artificial intelligence specifically, I’d also recommend wondering how our current understanding of <em>Homo sapiens</em> could shape the future development of AI. Of course, it’d be also fruitful to reflect on whether all this makes us become happier, or just makes us more ambitious to pursue happiness.</p> ]]></content><author><name>An Xuelong</name></author><category term="blog-post"/><category term="books-review"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[my review on Sapiens and Homo deus, books authored by Yuval Harari]]></summary></entry></feed>